<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Yathartha Joshi</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2018-04-29T12:24:59+05:30</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Yathartha Joshi</name>
   <email>yathartha32@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Got Selectd in GSoC</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/gsoc-selection"/>
   <updated>2018-04-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/gsoc-selection</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/gsoc.png&quot; style=&quot;width:30%;height:30%;float:left;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/public/sympy.png&quot; style=&quot;width:25%;height:25%;float:right;margin-right:100px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sorry for the late post!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/5583344046178304/#6097058637807616&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; were out on 23 April 2018 and guess what I got selected and will be working under &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sympy.org&quot;&gt;Sympy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for the next 3 months. I will be working on my project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1kcZCdQuY3XxgHPuSA8vvwc6O8AbVZ-nYskMuXIia9hA/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Solvers: Completing Solvers&lt;/a&gt;, during this period. I am really excited to work with such an amazing organization. I would like to thank all the mentors especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/asmeurer&quot;&gt;Aaron Meurer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/smichr&quot;&gt;Christopher Smith&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aktech&quot;&gt;Amit Kumar&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jksuom&quot;&gt;Kalevi Suominen&lt;/a&gt; for guiding me in my proposal and PR’s. My official mentor will be &lt;strong&gt;Amit Kumar&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase is the &lt;em&gt;Community Bonding Period&lt;/em&gt;, I will focussing on the following things before the coding period begans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setting up blog and synchronizing it with planet sympy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discussing possible means of communication, weekly meetings etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Planning the implementation of the project with Amit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Familiarizing with the codebase of Sympy and see how it may help solving the problems while implementing the project.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be having my end sems and practicals during this period but I will try to accomplish the above tasks whenever I get time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward for a wonderful summer ahead 😄	!!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Web Crawlers and Web Crawling</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/web-crawler"/>
   <updated>2017-07-07T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/web-crawler</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/web-crawlers.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:30%;height:30%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how a search engine comes up with the exact results when you type something in its query box? After all, there are trillions of results matching your search query. A fascinating process is at work behind it. It is the &lt;strong&gt;Web Crawler&lt;/strong&gt; that is responsible for accomplishing the task. So what is a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;web crawler&lt;/code&gt;, what it does and how it does, I will try to answer all these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is a Web Crawler&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Web Crawler&lt;/em&gt; or simply a &lt;em&gt;Crawler&lt;/em&gt; is a program that acts as an automated script which browses through the internet in a systematic way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web Crawlers are also known as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Spiders&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Robot&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SearchBot&lt;/code&gt; or simply &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Bot&lt;/code&gt;. Web crawlers are one of the most common used systems now-a-days. The most popular example is that &lt;em&gt;Google&lt;/em&gt; is using crawlers to collect information from all websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Search Engine Spider&lt;/code&gt; is a program that most search engines use to find what’s new on the Internet. The crawler looks at the keywords in the pages, the kind of content each page has and the links, before returning the information to the search engine. This process is known as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Web crawling&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides search engine, news websites need crawlers to aggregate data sources. It seems that whenever you want to aggregate a large amount of information, you may consider using crawlers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is Web Crawling Important&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me make you understand with an example to show why web crawling is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data lies in the heart of any business, even more if its tech related. With all the open standards of today like RSS feeds or APIs sharing data across systems have become relatively easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to read today’s financial news directly from your email inbox, you could simply subscribe to the provider’s (like Google News or BBC) RSS feed. Similarly, your system or application could also use a provider’s API to get upto date information.
But what about data that is unstructured or does not have RSS feeds for you to consume? How will you go about fetching them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider another simple example. Suppose you have a shopping site and have 1000 products. You want to make sure your prices are competitive. In order to do that, you will need to monitor your competitors’ sites and their prices for the same products. If there are a lot of products and lot of competitors it is going to be very difficult to do this without some automated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Web Crawling&lt;/code&gt; comes into picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Web Crawling&lt;/code&gt; technology was made popular by Google for its use in their search. They were the first to see the importance of immense amount of data on the web which was then not crawled and indexed. They capitalized on that – sent out thousands of crawlers to the web and indexed everything they could possibly find!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up let’s get few points summarized as to why web crawling is important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gather data for business intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Market research about the product or service you are offering.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Monitor competitor’s product or solution 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gather user behavior data to make your product perform better.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does a Web Crawler work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short as explained by &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/webmasters/answer/70897?hl=en&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; on how Google Search works, for web crawling procedure there are mainly three steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First, the search bot starts by crawling the pages of your site(&lt;strong&gt;Crawling&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then it continues indexing the words and content of the site(&lt;strong&gt;Indexing&lt;/strong&gt;), and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;finally it visit the links (web page addresses or URLs) that are found in your site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To control the way a spider looks to your website is by using a &lt;strong&gt;robots.txt&lt;/strong&gt; file. The first thing a spider is supposed to do when it visits your website is look for a file called &lt;em&gt;robots.txt&lt;/em&gt;. This file contains instructions for the spider on which parts of the website to index, and which parts to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another piece of information I would share is the following answer in &lt;strong&gt;Quora&lt;/strong&gt;, when asked&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are some ideas of how a startup can use web crawler scripts to drive growth?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/quora-web-crawler-answer.png&quot; style=&quot;height=30%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was just an idea about &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;web crawlers&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;web crawling&lt;/code&gt;. Hope, this might help you to get started with crawlers. Till then All the Best 👍 and Happy Coding 😃&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Python Script to get NASA's APOD</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/nasa-wall-python-script"/>
   <updated>2017-07-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/nasa-wall-python-script</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have always been worried about my desktop’s wallpaper. I find it a bit tedious to search the web for an image, download it and set it as my desktop’s wallpaper. So I thought to write a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python script&lt;/code&gt; that would do the job for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a bit enthusiast about space and astronomy, I thought to get wallpapers from NASA’s official site, and therefore I wrote the script. The script actually gets the wallpaper from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NASA's APOD(Astronomy Picture Of the Day)&lt;/code&gt; and sets it as your desktop wallpaper. So here is my github link to the script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Yathartha22/nasa&quot;&gt;NASA APOD script&lt;/a&gt;. Currently it works on Linux OS, I will try to make it platform independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till then enjoy with amazing and cool space pics from NASA 😃&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>API and Django Rest Framework</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/api-and-django-rest-framework"/>
   <updated>2017-06-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/api-and-django-rest-framework</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been learning Django, and meanwhile, I came across API and thought how to build them. Consequently, I found &lt;strong&gt;Django Rest Framework&lt;/strong&gt;, commonly known as DRF. Before going deep into the topic let’s get clear with the definition what actually an API is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;API as defined by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_programming_interface&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In computer programming, an Application Programming Interface (API) is a set of subroutine definitions, protocols, and tools for building application software. In general terms, it is a set of clearly defined methods of communication between various software components.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit technical, let me make it more simple for you. Think of an API as a waiter in a restaurant. You are sitting on a table with a menu of choices to order from and a kitchen is a part of the system that will prepare your order, what’s missing is the critical link to communicate your order to the kitchen and deliver food back to you. This is where a waiter or an API comes into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;API&lt;/strong&gt; is an interface between the &lt;em&gt;Application&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Program&lt;/em&gt;. You might have heard of Youtube API, what does it mean is Youtube API will be a set of functions or procedure that you can use to run youtube functionality on your website(or any application). A good API makes it easier to develop a program by providing all the building blocks. A programmer then puts the blocks together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess API term might have cleared by now. So let’s get started with what actually is DRF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DRF&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/DRF.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As defined in the official &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.django-rest-framework.org/&quot;&gt;documentation of DRS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Django REST framework is a powerful and flexible toolkit for building Web APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term REST stands for &lt;strong&gt;Representational State Transfer (REST).&lt;/strong&gt;  REST advocates that web applications should use HTTP as it was originally envisioned. Lookups should use GETrequests. PUT, POST, and DELETE requests should be used for creation, mutation, and deletion. I am not going into much detail about what REST is. You can refer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/a/671132/6446166&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; Stackoverflow answer for details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Django REST framework contains a wide set of out of the box features, but the core view class is very simple and framework, in general, is easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea behind of DRF is to clearly divide a model, the generalized wire representation (e.g. JSON, XML, etc.), and set of generic Class-Based-Views that can be customized to satisfy the specific API endpoint using Serializer that describes the mapping between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about DRF, which makes it different from other framework is that it allows developers to define URL structure and not rely on an auto-generated one, while others automate much of the conversion from Django models to REST endpoints, thus are less flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Django REST Framework includes built-in API browser for testing out newly developed API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DRF provides a set of authentication policies out of the box (including &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.django-rest-framework.org/api-guide/authentication#oauthauthentication&quot;&gt;OAuth1a&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.django-rest-framework.org/api-guide/authentication#oauth2authentication&quot;&gt;OAuth2&lt;/a&gt; and gives an opportunity to develop custom schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I have to learn a lot of stuff in DRF I will keep posting whatever new and interesting things I learn  &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Django</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/django"/>
   <updated>2017-06-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/django</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/django.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s been a long time that I haven’t written about anything. So I thought to write about what I am learning for the past few days &lt;strong&gt;Django&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will get started with the definition first&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Django is a high level python web framework. It is free and open source, written in python.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other framework, Django also supports MVC(&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;odel &lt;strong&gt;V&lt;/strong&gt;iew &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;ontroller) pattern. It follows MVC closely, however, it does use its own logic in the implementation. Because the “C(&lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;ontroller)” is handled by the framework itself and most of the excitement in Django happens in models, templates and views, Django is often referred to as an MTV(&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;odel &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;emplate &lt;strong&gt;V&lt;/strong&gt;iew) framework.
Not going into much detail what MVC or MTV is, just know that Django’s View is more like the Controller in MVC, and MVC’s View is actually a Template in Django. Therefore the name MTV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a bit of an introduction to what actually &lt;em&gt;Django&lt;/em&gt; is. The reason why I chose Django was that I was involved with Python(coding as well as open source) for quite a time so I thought why not try Python in web development, so I started with Django.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like the most about Django, is we can actually create dynamic websites really fast, you don’t need to worry about most things, you just define your data model and off you go. With Django, you can take Web applications from concept to launch in a matter of hours. Django takes care of much of the hassle of Web development so you can focus on writing your app without needing to reinvent the wheel. Another thing that I appreciate and like is Django’s community and resources. It has a huge community ready to help anytime &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/django/django&quot;&gt;Django’s open source community&lt;/a&gt;. Also it has it’s resources are properly documented &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.11/&quot;&gt;Django’s documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Django?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ridiculously fast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Django is designed to help developers take applications from concept to completion as quickly as possible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fully loaded&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Django includes dozens of extras you can use to handle common Web development tasks. Django takes care of user authentication, content       administration, site maps, RSS feeds, and many more tasks — right out of the box.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reassuringly secure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Django takes security seriously and helps developers avoid many common security mistakes, such as SQL injection, cross-site scripting, cross-site request forgery and clickjacking. Its user authentication system provides a secure way to manage user accounts and passwords.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exceedingly scalable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some of the busiest sites on the planet use Django’s ability to quickly and flexibly scale to meet the heaviest traffic demands.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incredibly versatile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Companies, organizations and governments have used Django to build all sorts of things — from content management systems to social networks  to scientific computing platforms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follwing are the well known sites built using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Django&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.userlogos.org/files/logos/motoko-chan/bitbucket.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 130px; height=200px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://1000logos.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Instagram-app-logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 100px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://ffp4g1ylyit3jdyti1hqcvtb-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/opendesign/files/2017/01/Mozilla-12jan-1500px_logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width:100px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/736x/88/8c/5e/888c5e49ac44fc34f572986c7b9d18c0--pinterest-logo-png-pinterest-account.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 100px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e5/NASA_logo.svg/200px-NASA_logo.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 100px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://assets2.onionstatic.com/onion/static/images/onion_fb_placeholder.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 160px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.russellheimlich.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2007/05/mahalo_logo.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 100px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.logcabin.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Washington-Post-Logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 170px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.underconsideration.com/brandnew/archives/eventbrite_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 150px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.brandsoftheworld.com/sites/default/files/styles/logo-thumbnail/public/112013/disqus-logo-blue-white.png?itok=UwOSMzby&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 90px;height=80px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details you can have a look &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/top-10-sites-built-django-framework-vladimir-bogdanov&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think if you are a &lt;em&gt;Python&lt;/em&gt; lover you should give &lt;em&gt;Django&lt;/em&gt; a try…!!  I will come up with more experiences with Django, till then All the best 👍 and Happy coding 😃&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>All about GSoC</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/gsoc-preparation"/>
   <updated>2017-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/gsoc-preparation</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://geekfeminismdotorg.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/gsoc2016logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is GSoC, What it takes it to be a part of GSoC and everything about GSoC.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GSoC is a platform which every student dreams of and I am one of those who really want to be a part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-actually-gsoc-is&quot;&gt;What actually GSoC is?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; is a global program focused on bringing more student developers into open source software development. Students work with an open source organization on a 3 month programming project during their break from school.
The primary aim of this program is to promote &lt;strong&gt;Open Source Software Development&lt;/strong&gt;. It was initiated in May 2005 and is still being conducted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selected students are provided with stipends by &lt;em&gt;Google&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pre-requisites&quot;&gt;Pre-requisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The requirements to be a part of GSoC is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must be at least 18 years of age&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must currently be a full or part-time student (or have been accepted for the fall term) at an accredited university as of the student     acceptance date.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-prepare-for-gsoc&quot;&gt;How to prepare for GSoC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, preparing for GSoC takes a lot of patience and dedication. I will try to cover my experience on what all difficulties I faced during my preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First of all you need to chose an organization for which you will be applying and working for the rest of months(if selected).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You should be well aware of what the organization does, who all are the lead developers, mentors and everything about the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also you should have spent quite a time working with the organization. I suggest you to start contributing as early as possible, because more the time you contribute to the organization the more chances it gets for you being selected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I started working with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sympy.org/en/index.html&quot;&gt;Sympy&lt;/a&gt; before 3 months of the GSoC time. I got along with Sympy’s development workflow and submitted few patches and even raised few issues. That is what has to be done to understand the organization properly. For reference on how to start contributing in Open Source you can have a read of my another blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://yaj22.wordpress.com/2017/02/12/contributing-to-open-source/&quot;&gt;Contributing To Open Source&lt;/a&gt;, in which I have tried to cover how to contribute in open source as a newbie.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After selecting the organization an application has to be sent suggesting your propsal. Start analysing what you will be proposing in the application. You can either propose a completely new project to work on or either you can chose to work on already established projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to prepare your application as strong as possible. There is around 14-15 days for you to prepare your application and submit it to the organization. Start working and understanding what has been propsed in the appliation. Try to summarize yourself in a brief and an appropriate manner. Include all the things you have done with the organization, even include your past experience, if any. You can even refer to the senior developers, previous year GSoCers who could advice you to improve the application. Submit your application soon, do not wait for the last moment. One can have a look over the previous years proposals for refreneces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After submitting the propsal be patient for about a month, because results won’t be out before that. Continue contributing and even if you are not selected don’t get yourself disheartened, because &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;there is always a second a chance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, you just need to be optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope these information might get you a start if you are willing to be a part of the prestigious GSoC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best and happy coding!! 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
